Finding Aid for the Book Artifacts Collection, circa 2345 B.C.-1993 A.D. (bulk circa 1510-1976)
The Bancroft Library
- Specialty Printing, W2
  - Metal pins, watch fobs, lapel buttons, reated objects (Panama Pacific International Exposition, 1915) and other items, W2S36
    - Watch fob: "Panama Pacific International Exposition San Francisco 1915", W2S36, No. 9
    - "IX Universala Kongreso de Esperanto 1915", W2S36, No. 10
    - Medal: "International Gas Congress San Francisco 1915", W2S36, No. 11
    - Medal: "Panama-Pacific Internation Exposition San Francisco 1915", W2S36, No. 12
    - Metal pin, shape of Liberty Bell, W2S36, No. 13
    - Lapel button: "GAA P.P.I.E.", W2S36, No. 14
    - Lapel button: "Panama-Pacific Internation Exposition 'You Helped' May 10, 1915", W2S36, No. 15
    - Lapel button: "Exposition Builders Panama-Pacific International Exposition", W2S36, No. 16
    - Lapel button: "Panama-Pacific International Exposition Presented April 10 1915 in recognition of services", W2S36, No. 17
    - Lapel button: "Panama-Pacific International Exposition Presented to the Crew of the U.S.N. Auxillary Jason for bringing foreign exhibits to the Exposition 1915", W2S36, No. 18
    - Sterling silver miniature of spade used by William Howard Taft, President of the United States, at Ground-Breaking, Panama-Pacific International Exposition, October 14, 1911, W2S36, No. 19
    - Display relating to the Congressional resolution authorizing the President to invite foreign countries to participate in the Panama-Pacific International Exposition, San Francisco, 1915, W2S36, No. 20
    - Pop-up mailing card: Victor Exhibition Palace of Liberal Arts, Panama-Pacific International Exposition, San Francisco, 1915, W2S36, No. 21
    - Pop-up mailing car: Victor Exhibition Palace of Liberal Arts, Panama-Pacific International Exposition, San Francisco, 1915, W2S36, No. 22
  - [Brass plate for cylinder press: label], W2S37
    - Brass plate for cylinder press: fruit box label, W2S37, No. 1
  - [Examples of tinting], W2S38
    - Examples of tinting encased in plastic, W2S38, No. 1-4
- Supplementary Collections, Z0-Z6
  Historical Artifacts (Z0)
  This collection includes miscellaneous historical artifacts, including a stencil set and plate with brush, gift of Sarah Randall Clifford.
  Beulah Mitchell Clute Collection (Z1)
  Original art and printed examples of the work of Beulah Mitchell Clute, artist-printer active in Berkeley form 1915 to the mid-1950s, are in the Bancroft Pictorial Collection. Linocut blocks and zinc photoengravings in line for her broadsides, note cards, Christmas cards, and table linens have been placed in the BART Collection. All are the gift of Mrs. Herbert Blasdale.
  Seals (Wax Impressions) (Z2)
  These wax impressions, chiefly of English royal seals, are of varying degrees of clarity. The earliest seal is that of William the Conqueror, the most recent, that of Elizabeth I.
  Seals (Z3)
  Some dies are badly worn; many readings are conjectural.
  Book Arts Medals (Z4)
  Medals collected by John Henry Nash commemorate persons, places, or events prominent in the history of book arts. More than thirty honor Gutenberg, either also or with Fust, Schöffer, or Seneferlder; Benjamin Franklin is generously represented; Coster, Dürer, the Didots, Daniel Eaton (“Three Times Accused of Sedition”), James Lackington (“Cheapest Booksellers in the World”), Pfister, the cities of Haarlem, Nuremberg, Ratisbon, and various book-related organizations figure in others. In addition there are several handsome Bodoni medals, the gift of Gleb A. Popoff.
  Printing the Guide (Z5)
  This section preserves, as a record of technological development, computer, and camera-ready copy from the 1985 printing of the first edition of The Guide to the Book Artifacts Collection. Included also are photographs taken for the Guide by Harry Summerfield.
  Commemorative Postage Stamps (Z6)
  Postage stamps and first-day covers relating to printing are from the estate of Roger Levenson.
  - Historical artifacts, Z0
    - Stencil set, 189?, Z0, No. 1
  - Beulah Mitchell Clute Collection, Z1
    - Prints, Proofs, Drawings, Z1I55, No. 1-44
    - Linocut blocks, Z1L48, No. 1-143
    - Zinc photoengravings in line, Z1Z4, No. 1-106
  - Seals (wax impressions), Z2
    - Elizabeth I, 1586-1603, Z2, No. 200
    - Henry VIII, 1532-1541, Z2, No. 201
    - Mary I, 1554-1556, Z2, No. 202
    - Henry IV, 1411, Z2, No. 203
    - Edward IV, 1470?, Z2, No. 204
    - Richard II, 1377-1399, Z2, No. 205
    - Henry VIII, 1532-1547, Z2, No. 206
    - Great Britain, Great Seal, 1651, Z2, No. 207
    - Anne of Brittany, 1499, Z2, No. 208
    - Henry VIII, 1542-1547, Z2, No. 209
    - Edward V, 1483, Z2, No. 210
    - Edward IV, 1469-1483?, Z2, No. 211
    - Edward III, 1340-1372, Z2, No. 212
    - Elizabeth I, 1586-1603, Z2, No. 213
    - Edward I, 1272-1307?, Z2, No. 214
    - Edward III, 1340-1372, Z2, No. 215
    - WIlliam I, 1066-1087, Z2, No. 216
    - Coventry, Z2, No. 217
    - Robert de Ferrer, 8th Earl of Derby, ca. 1265, Z2, No. 218
    - Not received, Z2, No. 219
    - Duchy of Cornwall Custom House, ca. 1400-1413, Z2, No. 220
  - Seals, Z3
    From Alan Nelson, Department of English, UCB - "The follwing are my readings, ranging from fairly certain to ignorant and highly conjectural, of seals in The Bancroft Librar. The letters which are underlined are particularly uncertain and conjectural. Further help needed!!" (Cannot underline in Webgen DB so refer to image from register)
    Not on shelf
    - S.CAPITVLI.LAREN.AD.CAVSIS, Z3B3219 (8 and 9)
    - SIGILLVM:+:BVRCENSIVM:+:OPIDI:+:IN:+:BIRCK:+:, Z3B3244 (3)
    - +LVDOVICVS:OVIRTVS.DEI.GRACIA.ROMANORVM.IMPERATOR.SEMPER.AVGVSTVS, Z3B3245 (4)
    - Can't read, Z3B3255 (7)
    - S.MANSIONARIORVM.CAPITVLI.S.GVMMARI.IN.LIRA.ETC., Z3B3313 and Z3B3314 (5 and 6)
    - Can't read (POSITIVE SEAL), Z3B3427 (7)
    - CONTRASIGILL SORTINO IN SVLENADORVSAS, Z3B3428 (11)
    - HEROLDVS DIGA BAVAR_ BVRCENSIS EP[ISCOPU]S, Z3B35506 (1)
    - SCABOLI LVDOVICI D[EI] G[RACIA] COMTALALI BHEM SACROLIMI ARCHID_.ELECT.DVC.BAVAR, Z3B3507 (2)
  - Books arts medals, Z4
    - Bodoni, Giovanni Battista, 1740-1813, Z4B61, No. 1-6
    - Book Club of California, Z4B64, No. 1
    - Colt, Samuel, 1814-1862, Z4C52, No. 1
    - Coster, Laurens, 1370-1440, Z4C56, No. 1
    - Borsenverein der Deutschen Buchhandler, 1836, Z4D36, No. 1-2
    - Didot, Pierre, 1761-1853, Z4D52, No. 1-2
    - Didot, Firmin, 1764-1836, Z4D53, No. 1-3
    - Dürer, Albecht, 1471-1528, Z4D86, No. 1-2
    - Eaton, Daniel Isaac, d. 1814, Z4E17, No. 1
    - Francis Joseph I, 1830-1896 (Antonelli Press), Z4F63, No. 1-2
    - Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790, Z4F64, No. 1-6
    - Franklin, Benjamin, Boston Latin School Medal, Z4F64B, No 1-6
    - Franklin, Benjamin and DeVinne, T.L, Z4F64D, No. 1-2
    - Franklin, Benjamin and Montyon, A.J.P.R.A., Z4F64M, No. 1-2
    - Franklin, Benjamin, National Export Exposition, Z4F64N, No. 1
    - Franklin, Benjamin and Washington, George, Z4F64W, No. 1
    - Gutenberg, Johann, Z4G76, No. 1-47
    - Gutenberg, Johann and Fust, Johann, Z4G76F, No. 1-5
    - Gutenberg, Johann and Fust, Johann, and Schoffer, Peter, Z4G76FS, No. 1
    - Gutenberg, Johann and Senefelder, Aloysius, Z4G76Se, No. 1-2
    - Haarlam, Z4H25, No. 1-5
    - Hawthorn, Nathaniel 1804-1864, Z4H28, No. 1
    - Lackington, James 1746-1815, Z4L13, No. 1-2
    - Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth 1807-1882, Z4L72, No. 1
    - Bibliopolae et Typographi, Lyons, 1723?, Z4L89, No. 1-2
    - Newton, Alfred Edward 1864-1940, Z4N52, No. 1
    - Nuremberg, 1740, Z4N76, No. 1
    - Paris, Impremerie Nationale, 1848, Z4P12, No. 1
    - Bibliopilae et Typographi, Paris, 1723, Z4P122, No. 1
    - Cercle de la Librairie de L'Imprimerie et de la Papeterie, Paris 1847, Z4P123, No. 1
    - Congres des Bibliothecaires et des Bibliophiles, Paris 1923, Z4P127, No. 1
    - Paterson Parchment Paper Company, 1935, Z4P16, No. 1
    - Pfister, Albrecht, fl. 1459-1464 and Sensenschmidt, Johann, Z4P28S, No. 1-2
    - Ratisbon, Z4R28, No. 1
  - Materials for printing the 1985 Guide, Z5
    - Typed Copy of the Guide to the BART Collection, Z5A3, No. 1
    - #4 Rider, Robin, Basf Enfora "800-6250 BPI" Tape, Z5B5, No. 1
    - Camera Ready Copy of the Guide to the BART Collection, Z5B6, No. 1
    - Groups of Ornaments, Z5C5, No. 1-50
    - Preliminary Paystub, Z5D6, No. 1
    - Negatives of the Guide's pages, Z5E2, No. 1-15
    - Materials Related to the Printing of the 1985 Guide, Z5E8, No. 1-2
    - Leaves from the 1985 Guide, Z5G7, No. 1-6
    - 1st Edition of the 1985 Guide, Z5H2, No. 1
  - Commemorative postage stamps, Z6
    - Collection of 14 Postage Stamps, Z6, No. 1-14
- The Merrymount Press Artifacts Collection, 1986; E13.B23 R44 1986